[SPEAKER_03]: Maybe I'll start with a simple one.
[SPEAKER_03]: I was reading about the abandonment of the tendencies that we have towards pleasant, unpleasant and neutral feelings.
[SPEAKER_03]: And there was...
[SPEAKER_03]: I'm not totally clear on the tendencies that are supposed to come from the neutral feelings.
[SPEAKER_03]: Specifically, it says
[SPEAKER_03]: When one is touched by neither painful nor pleasant feeling, if one understands, as it actually is, the origination, the disappearance, the gratification, the danger and the escape in regard to that feeling, then the underlying tendency to ignorance does not lie within this one.
[SPEAKER_03]: And this just confuses me.
[SPEAKER_03]: I don't understand one bit of it, except that it fuels ignorance, but I'm not sure how.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, the neutral feeling is the one that's pretty much not seen, generally, by people.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the feeling that's hardest to see for what it is, as a phenomenon that endures.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, oh, it's neither pleasant nor unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_00]: People might have an idea about it, but they cannot actually... You know, it's easy to see when you're feeling bad.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's obvious.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's easy to see when you're related with pleasure.
[SPEAKER_00]: But what it's not obvious is when it's kind of neither.
[SPEAKER_00]: And because it's not obvious, that's why that is felt unpleasantly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you don't know it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, when people feel neither, they don't find that peaceful and agreeable.
[SPEAKER_00]: They find that as a kind of, you know, dull, pressuring discomfort.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's... in the talks on our YouTube channel, I did a few on that, and it is practically... it's like, you know, when you're bored, how it starts.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't feel bad, but by not feeling good either, and by not having any kind of distraction to take your mind away from it, you start feeling unpleasantly.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that is still a neutral feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: But because it's not known, it's felt as a form of discomfort.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that lack of...
[SPEAKER_03]: So, we basically escalated on our own from neutral to, well, unpleasant afterwards.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, sort of, but I wouldn't say escalate, because ignorance is already there with that feeling, because it's not understood.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, there is no, like, a first point where that feeling is clear, and then you get confused, and then it escalates into pain.
[SPEAKER_00]: You already don't know it, when it is there, which means pain is already there with that lack of knowledge.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what the suttas, maybe even the same suttas, says.
[SPEAKER_00]: When it's not known, it's felt unpleasantly.
[SPEAKER_00]: When it's known, it's felt pleasantly.
[SPEAKER_00]: By the wise, they find, they understand that's where the peace is.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the ignorance is that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not knowing that, not understanding, not being able to endure the pressure of the neutral feeling, seeking the distraction out of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: All of that is what perpetuates that ignorance.
[SPEAKER_00]: Ignorance is not a lack of information or some, you know, metaphysical secret or something.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not being able to endure the discomfort of a neutral feeling, acting out of it, seeking the distractions, perpetuating it, feeding it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the ignorance that underlines it and that you keep sustaining in that very underlining it.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, when you do identify the neutral feeling,
[SPEAKER_03]: So, for example, the first way to see it would be to recognize, let's say, when you're bored or when you're looking for something like, it's not bad, but I could have something more.
[SPEAKER_03]: Would that be a good way to pin it down?
[SPEAKER_00]: Sure, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: When you have nothing to do, catch yourself before you start doing something.
[SPEAKER_00]: And see, like, why is it that you want to do it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Where is it rooted?
[SPEAKER_00]: Or is it because you don't want... you're already trying to prevent the boredom, even before it came, so to speak?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because often people always have something to do lined up.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the moment they sort of run out of things to do and calm down, they're already going for the next thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which is not, you know, often it's seen how I must do this, and this is this is necessary, but more often than not, actually, it's not, or certainly not as necessary.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yet, people have this accumulated pressure.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, no, I still must do this.
[SPEAKER_00]: And they confuse that pressure to be like a pressure of duty, but it's really pressure of escaping the boredom.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or, well, pressure of escaping the fear that comes if you don't distract yourself from boredom.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because boredom, if you sit with it, it's going to become very unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you refuse to do anything and just sit with yourself, it's going to result in anxiety, more often than not, for people that haven't been through that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why when you kind of relish the activity and finding things to do that you depend on.
[SPEAKER_03]: I remember hearing one of your talks where you challenged us to be bored and endure it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, like, even meditation practice for people becomes a something to do, so I don't get bored.
[SPEAKER_03]: Okay, thank you.
[SPEAKER_01]: I would actually have a question on meditation, if that's okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: Namely, the mindfulness of breathing meditation.
[SPEAKER_01]: This seems to be the most
[SPEAKER_01]: This is a commonly prescribed method of meditation in various dhamma talks by various teachers, very popular and widespread.
[SPEAKER_01]: But usually, this instruction in these dhamma talks stops at the feeling the breath coming in and out of your body, maybe feeling the entire body.
[SPEAKER_01]: Some say feeling the body of the breath,
[SPEAKER_01]: But, reading the suttas, you can see that mindfulness of breathing was much more elaborately described, or this instruction was much more elaborate.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, there are such additional units to this instruction, such as, you know, tranquilizing the body, experiencing rapture, experiencing pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, I'm also wondering about this experiencing the mental formations.
[SPEAKER_01]: Experiencing the entire mind, and then gladdening, concentrating, and liberating the mind, and also contemplating impermanence, fading away, cessation, liberation, liberation, as well as contemplating the elements of the elements, so the four elements plus space, and kindness, and so the brahmanikāras.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I was wondering,
[SPEAKER_01]: Do you think... was this meant to be like a step-by-step instruction on what to do in one sitting?
[SPEAKER_01]: And in that case, I don't think I remember all the motions when I have to... when I sit down and... Or was it just, you know, just general guidelines on what kind of sentiments or, I don't know, dispositions to
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, first you need to become a sotāpanna, as the sutta itself says.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's the something that everybody seems to be overlooking and ignoring.
[SPEAKER_00]: The Buddha told ānāpānasati to the monks that were very much already on the path and they haven't quite completed it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, he said, oh, well, let me teach those who still have work to do.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which means it does not apply to people that can't even have the sign of their mind and have the right view.
[SPEAKER_00]: It simply doesn't apply.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's going to be misunderstood, misperformed, or as that other sutra says, mismeditated, undermeditated, overmeditated, premeditated, everything else, but not meditated.
[SPEAKER_00]: So really, that should be the concern.
[SPEAKER_00]: Getting the right view.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, what samādhi is, that will be known through that right view.
[SPEAKER_00]: But just to answer your theoretical aspect of ānāpānasati, no, it's not meant to be done as a step-by-step.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like the most comprehensive
[SPEAKER_00]: approach to the practice of mindfulness, on account of an pretty much inherent, inseparable bodily activity, in every possible aspect, they will absolutely remove any traces of ignorance left.
[SPEAKER_00]: But more often than not, monks were just, you know, doing it in that, in the broadest sense, how every description starts.
[SPEAKER_00]: Knowingly he breathes in, knowingly he breathes out.
[SPEAKER_00]: And there was another sutra where a monk said, oh, that's how he practices it, and he abandons sensuality of the past, sensuality of the future, and sensuality of the present.
[SPEAKER_00]: He has no more sensual desires, because he has fully developed mindfulness of breathing on the level of knowingly breathe in, knowingly breathe out.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then the Buddha said, yeah, that's fine, but you should do even more, and then goes into those other steps.
[SPEAKER_00]: In other words, that monk still had work to do, on a subtle level, which he wouldn't have completed if he didn't, obviously, refine further that mindfulness of breathing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, because it continues with the entering the jhānas, and it's a...
[SPEAKER_00]: But again, see, that's the whole, like...
[SPEAKER_00]: All of that follows on its own, as a result of the right view, which means it would be closer to the right ānāpānasati, say, for somebody without a right view, it will be closer for them to do the meditation, mindfulness of breathing correctly, not by watching their nostrils or breathing or following the steps, but by actually seeing the reason behind them wanting to do it in the first place.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why do I want to do this particular mindfulness of breathing?
[SPEAKER_00]: What am I hoping for?
[SPEAKER_00]: Where are my motivations rooted?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because they're still there.
[SPEAKER_00]: They will be enduring there.
[SPEAKER_00]: They will be the reasons for your action, the reason for your effort.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, are you trying to gain something as a result of it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Or are you trying to undo that which already prevents you from having the right view?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because right view is not gained.
[SPEAKER_00]: Right view is uncovered.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a completely opposite direction of where people usually go for.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it goes against the stream, against the grain.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's pretty much the nature of that, knowing the motivation behind your action.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's behind the grain of your action, behind the direction where you're heading to.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, whatever meditation you want to be doing, it's more important to know why and what for.
[SPEAKER_00]: And don't just take it for granted as something that I must do, because Buddhists meditate, and whatever comes out of it, it will be good for me.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, yeah, as many Suttas say, more often than not, people like that would end up meditating with their own sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which means no good will come out of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that whole notion of what concentration in itself is good,
[SPEAKER_00]: That's a very relative statement.
[SPEAKER_00]: Concentration itself is neither good nor bad.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just a state of mind directed upon something.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's the motivation behind that directing that what determines your intention, basically, as we spoke in the last Sunday.
[SPEAKER_00]: Your intention determines whether, you know, what you're about to do is rooted in... is good or not.
[SPEAKER_00]: Is it rooted in desire, aversion and so on?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the whole point is to recognize that, where the problem is, that it's not in what you're doing as much in terms of meditation and what technique and how to go about it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's really on the level as to what for and what you're hoping to achieve with it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Are you clear?
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, do you know exactly what this meditation is supposed to result in?
[SPEAKER_00]: Or you're just doing it and then you're basically hoping for some agreeable experiences that will be of the spiritual kind.
[SPEAKER_00]: Means there is no knowledge to begin with.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So you're just chasing the novelties.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, not you specifically, just in general, who I was doing it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Actually, I was reading Sutta number 64, Mahāmāluṅkā, Mahāmāluṅkā Sutta.
[SPEAKER_01]: I think that's a brilliant synthesis of everything also that you just said.
[SPEAKER_01]: Basically, because it distinguishes between, so the Buddha distinguishes between
[SPEAKER_01]: You have the tūjana there, you have the ordinary person, and then you have someone who has been trained, so, I don't know, ārya.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, the way he...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the thing is, the question is how to escape, for example, so how to escape from identity view, so the five lower factors among these, also the identity view, and it's...
[SPEAKER_01]: And he says, when you teach the dhamma to someone for the cessation of personality view, then their mind must really enter into this.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the first precondition, if I understood this correctly, is what you've been saying all along.
[SPEAKER_01]: This is seclusion from sensual pleasures.
[SPEAKER_01]: This is the precondition for them to even... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sensual pleasure in unwholesome states.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, absolutely.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I like how, you know, the Buddha goes on to explain that whatever exists in form, feeling, perception, formations and consciousness, which is basically everything there is, right?
[SPEAKER_01]: Everything that we can see, experience.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Everything you must see as impermanent, as causing suffering or unsatisfaction, and end not.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, and the only reason you need to see these things as causing suffering is not just like to torture yourself or cause pain to yourself.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's only because, by default, they're seen as agreeable and friendly, while they're not.
[SPEAKER_00]: And there are other suttas where the Buddha compares, like, you know, your own mind to, like, basically, like an assassin that pretends to be a friend, but just really wants to kill you.
[SPEAKER_00]: See, the danger is not in much in effect that an assassin wants to kill you.
[SPEAKER_00]: The danger is in you thinking he's your friend.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you stop thinking that he's your friend, he can't surprise you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thus, doesn't matter how much of an assassin he is, you always see where he is.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the problem is not in the mind wanting to kill you or the aggregates wanting to cause you suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: The problem is in you not seeing that because you keep holding the view that they're friendly, that they're agreeable, that they are yours.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, yours...
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: This is difficult to say.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay, so you can see... Well, yours...
[SPEAKER_00]: They're seen as yours, not as a choice.
[SPEAKER_00]: Seeing them as yours is the result of seeing them as friendly and non-dangerous.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, automatically, they're taken as mine.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why you contemplate danger, just to the extent of not taking them as mine.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, you let the assassin be.
[SPEAKER_00]: And he can't surprise you, and you're fine.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, would you say that by seeing how uncomfortable this all, the discomfort that this causes, all of these forms, feelings, perceptions, so, how much suffering there is in those aggregates, just by that, you can see that if it was really, if it was truly yours, you would make sure that it would be pleasant, at least,
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah, you can, obviously, you have to keep contemplating that, you have to keep reminding yourself of that, but before all of that, your actions must already be aligned up with that principle of, oh, this is not mine, this is not worth it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because often people would not have sufficient amount of sense restraint and guarding of the sense doors, and then they try to contemplate this on top of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that's why it cannot take the root, or not as much.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because their own actions are contradicting what they are doing, what they are contemplating.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, precepts, sense restraint and guarding the sense doors.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the prerequisite that really matches what you're contemplating later.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you need to have it before.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: What would you say about this?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, turning away...
[SPEAKER_01]: The Buddha says, turn your mind away from these states.
[SPEAKER_01]: Turn them away, but then the next question is, what do I turn them towards?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, where do I go then?
[SPEAKER_01]: Where should I turn my mind?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, no, you don't turn it towards... you don't turn it towards a new thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: You just turn it, as I said, to the extent... to the extent that you were turned towards this as friendly and acceptable,
[SPEAKER_00]: You turn away from that friendliness and you don't accept it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you don't acquire a new thing now, because that will become your sense of self again.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you turn away to the extent that you will turn towards it, but you don't turn away to find something new, because then your mind will become established upon that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, pull your attention back.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, see, you pull your attention back and you'll be attending that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's going to become another thing you're looking at.
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, your own question implies that.
[SPEAKER_00]: What do I turn it towards?
[SPEAKER_00]: As in, there must be something I must attend to.
[SPEAKER_01]: How do you disperse that spotlight of attention?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, you can't disperse the attention because that's part of the aggregates, but you can know the context of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, but you don't attend it, you don't make it into another object, or when you do, you at least don't lose the context of that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, again, that's on the level of the knowledge.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, things that you know, even in mundane terms, like, whatever, you know, your knowledge, basic knowledge that you have in regard to things, you don't need to constantly be attending that on a day-to-day basis in order to remember it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not at all.
[SPEAKER_00]: Quite the opposite.
[SPEAKER_00]: You need to attend things when you don't know them.
[SPEAKER_00]: When you actually get to understand them, you stop thinking about it, you stop attending it, and when that knowledge is needed, it comes back, because that's what understanding is.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it goes the same for the dhamma practice.
[SPEAKER_00]: When that man asked the Buddha, oh, does the Tathāgata, does he prepare these answers?
[SPEAKER_00]: to the various questions that people ask him.
[SPEAKER_00]: And he said, well, let me ask you in return and that will give you the answer.
[SPEAKER_00]: You are the master charioteer and making of the chariots.
[SPEAKER_00]: Do you, if somebody comes and asks you about various parts of the chariots, do you need to prepare the answer?
[SPEAKER_00]: Or do you know it right away?
[SPEAKER_00]: He says, oh, I know it right away.
[SPEAKER_00]: If somebody were to wake me up in the middle of the night, I will know the answer anyway, because I am the master of charity.
[SPEAKER_00]: I fully understood the principles behind how it works, how it's made.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the Buddha said, so is the same for Tathāgata.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, he doesn't need to prepare the answer, because he fully understood it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, knowledge, really, just knowledge of the universal characteristics of your experience, cannot be undone and cannot be forgotten.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's why it results in liberation.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not perfect attention, 100%, undivided, never kind of sways.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, that's the basically unenlightened mind idea of what enlightenment is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Full absorption into something that's outside of me, that will save me, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, actually, it's the same thing in the instruction of meditation that I was asking about before.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because the Buddha also says all breaths are known,
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, knowingly he breathes in, knowingly he breathes out.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not he breathes in feeling his nostrils or sensations in his chest.
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, you know you're already breathing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why do you need more?
[SPEAKER_00]: Why is that knowledge not enough to your mind?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, because of your wrong assumptions.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, really, the training of the mind is to recognize what it already knows,
[SPEAKER_00]: And realize that it's enough.
[SPEAKER_00]: That knowledge is enough if you sustain it and protect it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the training of the mind is not basically to sort of develop experiences on its own terms, but what the mind deems agreeable and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because what the mind deems agreeable is sensuality of one kind or the other.
And this knowledge
[SPEAKER_01]: During meditation or during whatever activity, this knowledge also will self... you know, all the other steps will self-generate.
The rapture will self-generate.
[SPEAKER_00]: Pleasure will be there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you sustain it sufficiently enough, develop your mind, becomes imperturbable, then yes, everything else will follow.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what I said before.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what you said before.
[SPEAKER_01]: And now, yeah, these two sutas are very much interconnected.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it really comes down to sort of curbing the tendency to follow the steps and find the next steps at the expense of that which you already know.
[SPEAKER_00]: See, everybody who sits down to practice meditational breathing knows that they are already breathing.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that ceases to be enough.
[SPEAKER_00]: The mind stops noticing it and wants something more palpable.
[SPEAKER_00]: I want the feeling of lightness.
[SPEAKER_00]: I want nostrils to feel.
[SPEAKER_00]: I want the lungs... Why is the knowledge not enough?
[SPEAKER_00]: Why is the knowledge so abstract when it's actually quite factual?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because the mind is not trained to recognize that level for what it is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Mind is dependent on more palpable things, because mind has been acting towards the sense objects its own life.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's the measure of its existence, the senses.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's exactly why even the basic knowledge, even as an instruction, it's not that people... No, but tell me... Tell me the steps.
[SPEAKER_00]: Tell me what I observe and what motions I do, because anything subtler than that is felt like an abstract theory, yet they know that they're breathing at any given time.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's nothing more factual than that.
[SPEAKER_01]: This is the peaceful, this is the sublime, and this is what you actually, in fact, then turn away, turn your mind away from and towards.
[SPEAKER_01]: This is what you turn... Yeah, you can say that.
[SPEAKER_00]: That knowledge will basically turn your mind away from things that it shouldn't have been... well, it shouldn't have been there in the first place.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That knowledge will prevent you from
[SPEAKER_00]: Regarding those things as friendly, agreeable and as yours.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I find this very useful.
[SPEAKER_01]: Buddha says, be aware that space is infinite.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you're aware that space is infinite, there's not much place for thoughts there.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's not much place for perceptions, formations, consciousness, anything, anywhere.
[SPEAKER_01]: So it's like the mind completely expands.
[SPEAKER_01]: He's talking about the deathless.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: He said that nothingness is something.
[SPEAKER_00]: To that extent.
[SPEAKER_00]: It is a phenomenon.
[SPEAKER_00]: The absence of certain things, so it's nothing, it's emptiness and all these negative sort of phenomena are positive in themselves for what they are.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not a mystical experience, it's just factual.
[SPEAKER_00]: Empty of lust, empty of aversion, empty of delusion.
[SPEAKER_03]: Before we continue to the next topic, I just wanted to check if I understood something correctly.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, when I was reading, I don't know, was it the same sutra or a different one?
[SPEAKER_03]: I don't know.
[SPEAKER_03]: But there was... it said, as they're breathing in and breathing out, they think about different things.
[SPEAKER_03]: And the way I saw it, the breath was just a trigger.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's a reference point.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's like an anchor.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, ānāpānasati is the same as satipaṭṭhāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: The breathing is always there, as I said in other talks, underneath your thoughts, your feelings, everything else you're concerned about or related about.
[SPEAKER_00]: Underneath all of that, this body is still breathing there.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, knowledge of that is what anchors you from being too driven, too far away in those thoughts and forgetting where the anchor is.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's not so much about wondering how you're breathing and how it feels like, it's just... No, no, no, not at all.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, it's knowing that you're breathing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Knowingly it breathes in, knowingly it breathes out.
[SPEAKER_00]: If that's fully developed, to the extent that it can be developed, all those other steps will become apparent and follow out of that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, I got my answer.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thank you very much.
[SPEAKER_01]: We have a question here.
[SPEAKER_01]: Could you please say something about the role of faith in dhamma practice?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, faith in dhamma practice is, as I said many times before, it's like faith you need to have in a doctor, that you think he might be able to help you.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you have absolutely no faith in what the doctor says,
[SPEAKER_00]: You won't even try the medicine that he prescribes.
[SPEAKER_00]: So... but equally, if the medicine is not working, you don't need to have faith in that doctor, because you saw that his instruction didn't work.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's when you change the doctor.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's not a blind faith that you must remain faith... full of faith towards the end... like towards... for the rest of your life.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the faith that you can be helped,
[SPEAKER_00]: In terms of the dhamma practice, and that faith should then be practiced out of, and eventually replaced with the knowledge that, yes, this medicine worked, and I'm healed.
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't need to have a faith in this doctor anymore, because his medicine worked, and now I'm confident that it was the right instruction.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why in the sutta, the person who gets the right view, their faith gets replaced as, how do we call it, confirmed confidence.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now, they know for themselves that the medicine works because they can see themselves healing.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's certainly not the faith that would be on the level of, oh, I have faith the Buddha was the greatest and I'll be saved on account of that faith.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, you know, what in Christianity is often found.
[SPEAKER_00]: Mind you, in Buddhism, it's often found.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's the faith that should make you practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, we have another question.
[SPEAKER_01]: This one is, what exactly is right view and how do you get to the right view?
[SPEAKER_00]: Keeping the precepts, seeing the danger in the slightest fault, guarding the sense doors, being moderate in eating, avoiding company, living in seclusion, and that will make you notice your mind for what it is.
[SPEAKER_00]: And when you do, it won't be too hard to see it as something that doesn't belong to you.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that would be the right view.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, impermanent suffering and non-self.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, people think I must see that, and having not fulfilled all the requirements before that, they will not gonna see it.
[SPEAKER_00]: If they have fulfilled all the requirements before that, they will see it, even if they don't make much effort to see it.
[SPEAKER_03]: I was reading a little bit about non-self as well, and
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, some things are very clear, like all the things you should not consider as self, but then that leaves us with the question, what remains?
[SPEAKER_03]: So, if we take all of this away, the guidelines, the criteria that were stated, were something that is permanent and something that we have control over.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, what in your opinion would be then
[SPEAKER_03]: qualified to be called self.
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't quite understand.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, what is permanent and what do you have control over?
[SPEAKER_03]: So, in one of the suttas, it said, so, if things are impermanent, they cause suffering and therefore should not be considered as a self or mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: And then, similarly, it said, if things were mine, then I would have control over them.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: And since I don't have control over them, they're not mine.
[SPEAKER_03]: So,
[SPEAKER_03]: Many different suttas say a lot about all the things that are not self.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: I was wondering, what remains?
[SPEAKER_00]: Nothing.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the whole point.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's nothing worth being calling self, nothing worth owning.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if you do, to that extent, you will be liable to suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the whole nothingness practice.
[SPEAKER_03]: But, for example, if I think who I am,
[SPEAKER_03]: I think about all the choices I made in my life that led me to this point.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, at any point in life, I could have made a different choice and I would have become a different person.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, if I consider these choices, all the past choices, don't they fill this criteria?
[SPEAKER_03]: I mean, they're permanent.
[SPEAKER_03]: Once they're done, they're done.
[SPEAKER_03]: You cannot change them.
[SPEAKER_03]: And you have control over them.
[SPEAKER_03]: You might not have the control about the circumstances you are in.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sure, you have a degree of control.
[SPEAKER_00]: But did you have a choice?
[SPEAKER_00]: Did you have choice in the options that were presented to you, that you chose from?
[SPEAKER_03]: No.
[SPEAKER_03]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the circumstance, I would say.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, your choice of control is always second to the circumstance.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it can never be the control of ownership, because it's always within that which you cannot own.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the choice you have, it's like a choice of driving a car down the cliff.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can choose to turn left and choose to turn right, but you can't stop it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, nobody denies that there is a phenomenon of control and choice, but you want to include that in that which is not liable to your choice, which cannot be penetrated by your choice and your control.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's exactly why I asked you for the options.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, you chose this on account of this, but did you have a say in what arose for you as the options of choosing?
[SPEAKER_02]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you never will.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, even the permanence of the choice is only relatively within the impermanence of the options.
[SPEAKER_03]: Okay, so...
[SPEAKER_03]: It would be foolish to say that anyone has full control over it, but couldn't we define ourselves relative to the situation?
[SPEAKER_03]: Or would that cause suffering?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, you can, sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, no, you can.
[SPEAKER_00]: Again, you can define yourself in a relative way, but that's not the problem, nor the point.
[SPEAKER_00]: The point is that any form of definition will kind of
[SPEAKER_00]: Feed the assumption that, to the extent that there is a control, to that extent your sense of self is justified.
[SPEAKER_00]: But see, if you see it correctly as a relative thing, like, sense of self is not seen as a relative.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even if you talk about it in theory as a relatively arisen or formed, fundamentally, sense of self is the owner and the master of this experience.
[SPEAKER_00]: But what kind of master is a relative master?
[SPEAKER_00]: Only a deluded master would say, I'm a master, ignoring his own relativity.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if he is relative, he is not in control.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thus, he is not the master.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's all you need to see.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't need to destroy that sense of relative self.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or deny it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or find something greater.
[SPEAKER_00]: You just need to disown it completely.
[SPEAKER_00]: And leave it be.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'll have to think on that.
[SPEAKER_01]: But thank you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just a quick note.
[SPEAKER_01]: Would you say that this self-determination or self-definition, it is sort of a constant and very fast exercise in accumulating and combining memories?
[SPEAKER_00]: Exercise performed by whom?
[SPEAKER_01]: By what?
[SPEAKER_01]: It happens really fast.
In cases of
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, all of that is unified already by the sense of self.
[SPEAKER_01]: It happens very fast.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I believe this happens really fast in our minds.
[SPEAKER_01]: Every
[SPEAKER_01]: Every regaining of consciousness, this very slight moment where the memories fall back into place as mosaic piece.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, see, how can you know then the moment before that happens?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because the moment before that happens, everything is blank.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, what are you saying?
[SPEAKER_00]: The blankness is then the truth?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, how do you know that that blankness is not owned?
[SPEAKER_00]: What makes you think that it's not owned?
[SPEAKER_01]: It's too empty to be owned.
[SPEAKER_01]: Nothing to call on to.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, you have to have the first memory and then stack them all up.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, again, see, the blankness is already a memory.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, what you call a first memory, it's not a first memory.
[SPEAKER_00]: Blankness before that is a previous memory.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, what is then the first memory?
[SPEAKER_00]: It's an infinite loop.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why it's impossible to see what you're referring to.
[SPEAKER_00]: Blankness before the memory can only be known as a memory.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thus, it's a contradiction in terms.
[SPEAKER_01]: Suppose you wake up, you know, you've had a slight case of amnesia.
[SPEAKER_01]: Wake up, you have no idea.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just no idea.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sure, you're like a newborn baby, yeah?
[SPEAKER_01]: The memories
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, then, okay, this is where I came from, this is what I did before that, and then this cracks up really fast and there it is.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's your personality there again.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, everything, now I can function.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay, but say, say like this, say you wake up from amnesia and your memories don't come back.
Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So what do you think?
[SPEAKER_00]: That state after amnesia, is that state pure?
[SPEAKER_00]: Or is that state equally corrupted and based on ignorance and ownership and not seeing impermanence?
[SPEAKER_01]: I think it's just by no means anywhere near enlightenment and seeing the infinite or the deathless at all.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that brings us exactly to what we said.
[SPEAKER_00]: Memories and your sense of self that came out of it, it's relative and remains relative.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, whether you remove it, whether you erase the memories, whether you catch the first moment before the memories, that's... all of that is already owned.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what the Buddha said, that even like the newborn baby, that doesn't have the memories, has not developed sensual appetites, has not corrupted itself.
[SPEAKER_00]: The mind, the senses, are already underlined by all the asavas, by the tendencies, underlying tendencies towards sensuality, towards craving, towards views.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which means, it's not a question of catching the first moment,
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, the second moment, the question is abandoning the whole picture.
The whole thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it's... it's... you can just see that it's just... it's a... it's a conglomerate.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, but it's irrelevant.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whether it's a conglomerate, or if it's a one thing, if it happens very slowly, if it happens very fast, happens within the framework.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's the framework that needs to be abandoned.
[SPEAKER_00]: And framework is not happening very fast.
[SPEAKER_00]: Framework is there from the moment you're born.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, that's always there, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, so that's the point.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thus, how many memories you accumulate, and if you're trying to forget or undo, all of that is second to the problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: The problem is underlying tendencies towards ownership, that are pretty much manifested, they start from the beginning.
[SPEAKER_00]: As I said, baby has no sense of self, that has developed on account of choices and so on, yet it keeps acting out of these underlying tendencies, which is why it develops the sense of self.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why I keep saying, the sense of self is not the problem, it's the symptom of an underlying problem, acting out of pleasurable feeling, acting out of neutral feeling, acting out of uncomfortable feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sense of self will be generated one way or the other.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you zoom in, if you really explore what's happening there at that level, look at the taṇha behind this, this magnetism, really zoom into that,
[SPEAKER_00]: No, no, no, no.
[SPEAKER_00]: You need to zoom out.
[SPEAKER_00]: Framework.
[SPEAKER_00]: Zoom out.
[SPEAKER_00]: Context.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not zoom in.
[SPEAKER_00]: The opposite direction.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what I'm saying.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not about catching the moment before or after.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's about zooming out far enough to see the framework there.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's where dhamma is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, you see that dhamma in
[SPEAKER_01]: Zooming out as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: Maybe you will, because it's probably... That's the only place you will see it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's... dhamma is not a momentary response.
[SPEAKER_00]: Dhamma is basically the whole direction of your mind already on the level of that framework.
Okay, maybe... maybe we're talking at cross purposes here.
I...
[SPEAKER_01]: I was thinking of exploring a certain emotion
[SPEAKER_01]: Really feeling it, really going in there, into that, eh, the feeling, really exploring, exploring it from within.
[SPEAKER_01]: And at a certain point, you will feel this, this humongous pull, the pull of personality.
[SPEAKER_00]: And when you feel like you're in contact... No, I think we're talking about the same thing, but I keep trying to point the opposite direction of what you're saying.
[SPEAKER_00]: See, you don't explore the feeling by getting into the feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: That basically means making it even more particular, which means falling away from the nature of the feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: You need to zoom out.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, instead of going to feel it more, you zoom out to know it more.
[SPEAKER_00]: Know what's already there, whichever way it's all there.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't need to make it felt differently to get to understand it better.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whichever way it's felt, you want to know it to that extent.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the framework I'm talking about.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's the opposite of falling onto the particular level.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's staying on that general, the background I often talk about.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's where the taṇha is.
That's where the taṇha is, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, next question.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, eh... Bhante, thank you again for, eh...
[SPEAKER_02]: Your willingness to give this question an answer.
[SPEAKER_02]: This is something that is quite interesting to me.
[SPEAKER_02]: Namely, to what degree, if at all, it's even possible to meaningfully talk about self within the Buddhist framework.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because, from what I've heard from your, some of your talks, it's not...
[SPEAKER_02]: Some people have this very
[SPEAKER_02]: I would say, simplistic understanding of what non-self is supposed to be, often it is understood either as a simple negation of the self, or they go down the Humean line, where they think that basically it's more or less a mosaic of, you know, aggregates, and then they say, well, there's no self, because in every moment of experience, you have these constituents.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, if you break this down, this is who I am.
[SPEAKER_02]: But this, this is just,
[SPEAKER_02]: I would say a very experientially naïve way of thinking about it.
[SPEAKER_02]: But the thing is, for instance, when I was reading this sutta, All the Taints, it ends up with a list of basically all the views that are wrong with regards to the self.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, all the views that arise from essential desire, being, and ignorance.
[SPEAKER_02]: Can I read them out?
[SPEAKER_00]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, he says, eh...
[SPEAKER_02]: These are the six views that arise in someone who basically is ignorant, if we oversimplify.
[SPEAKER_02]: Self exists for me.
[SPEAKER_02]: No self exists for me.
[SPEAKER_02]: I perceive self with self.
[SPEAKER_02]: I perceive not-self with self.
[SPEAKER_02]: I perceive self with not-self.
[SPEAKER_02]: And everlasting, enduring self.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, everlasting, enduring self.
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_02]: Let's put this aside.
[SPEAKER_02]: Let's say that, you know, for the most part, even in most of, say, Western thought nowadays, there will be very few people who would be willing to adopt some view of this type.
[SPEAKER_02]: But the other views are either present in everyday experience or in most of philosophical accounts that you would find.
[SPEAKER_02]: For instance, you might say someone like
[SPEAKER_02]: Kusar would say that, you know, I perceive self with self, so you have a transcendental self that perceives the empirical self.
[SPEAKER_02]: Or many similar might say, okay, well, this transcendental self is not really a self, it's a non-self.
[SPEAKER_02]: But all this is wrong.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, I'm just curious, you know, there would seem that there is a certain place for the self, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_02]: It is naive to say that non-self is simply a negation of
[SPEAKER_02]: I'm not particularly keen on the idea that it's not.
[SPEAKER_02]: In the past, I would be.
[SPEAKER_02]: But now,
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: There is self.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not yours.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the Buddha never said there is no self.
[SPEAKER_00]: He said that which is self is not yours.
[SPEAKER_02]: And there's a big difference.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's removing the ownership.
[SPEAKER_00]: It will remove the sense of self.
[SPEAKER_00]: People... people think I own things because I am.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's other way around.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's because you keep taking things as mine through sensuality, aversion and ignorance.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why you are.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why you have generated that sense of self that you cannot step outside of.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a symptom.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a symptom of ownership.
[SPEAKER_00]: You remove the ownership, sense of self cannot persist, or not to the same extent.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why ātavāda is a view.
[SPEAKER_00]: See, there is a sense of self as a result of careless ownership, not seeing impermanence, not restraining your actions.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that self that has been generated through such actions, you put first.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's the ātavāda.
[SPEAKER_00]: You think that is the first thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I own things because I am.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, it's because you keep owning individual things, that's why you are.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why that sense of self is there, and that's why the view on top of it is there.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's not a... you don't develop the experience of not-myself through figuring it out.
[SPEAKER_00]: You develop it through purifying your behavior that has been feeding it and sustaining it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then you'll see that that sense of self does not belong to you.
[SPEAKER_00]: And thus, it cannot be called self, truly.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why when people came to the Buddha and said, ah, so Master Gautama says there is no self.
[SPEAKER_00]: And he would be quiet.
[SPEAKER_00]: He wouldn't even reply to that because it's a completely... well, it's a question completely based on that wrong assumption that they don't see.
[SPEAKER_00]: Ah, so there is a sense of self that Master Gautama knows.
[SPEAKER_00]: He wouldn't... he would reply to that either.
[SPEAKER_00]: But practically speaking, that sense of self that is yours, remove that part of this is mine, and it won't be sense of self anymore.
[SPEAKER_00]: But don't try to remove the whole thing by saying, oh, the self doesn't exist.
[SPEAKER_00]: If it doesn't exist, what are you referring to as non-existing?
[SPEAKER_00]: There has to be something that's being designated when people say, oh, there is no self.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's that whole, the view permutation.
[SPEAKER_00]: With self, he sees self.
[SPEAKER_00]: It has to be... sense of self has to be either on immediacy level or on the level of reflection.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if he were to undo the ownership,
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the ownership part is what makes it the self.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not that thing that is there, taken to be the self.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because when the Buddha said, what is it that, you know, Putujana takes a self, oh, it's the form, it's the feeling, it's the perception, it's the intentions and the consciousness.
[SPEAKER_00]: There is nothing.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, all the phenomena generally, your sense of self will be resting upon something, because your sense of self will be resting upon the ownership of something.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, if I understand correctly, if
[SPEAKER_03]: You remove this ownership, you also remove the attachments you have to it, and therefore you would see it more objectively.
[SPEAKER_03]: Is this the difference?
[SPEAKER_00]: Sort of.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's basically if you say, you know, you keep eating food that doesn't agree with you, and your whole body is suffering, you're having headaches, and who knows what else, and you don't know the reason.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't know that it's because of the food.
[SPEAKER_00]: So now, you... sometimes you have a headache like this, but if you concentrate on something else, headache disappears, then you think maybe...
[SPEAKER_00]: But either way, you keep eating the food that it's making your condition worse.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, you find out that that was the problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: You stop eating the food that was bothering you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sufficient time needs to pass, basically, until the body recovers, and the headache will slowly dissipate and not come back.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's what will happen to the sense of self.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not that you're gonna lose your head that used to hurt.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're just gonna lose the pain of that which still remains there.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that sense of self, that sense of an individual that's still making choices, that remains.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the emotional, eh... ownership of it, that's gone.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that is an arahant.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what people cannot under... think... or either cannot understand, or think arahant is this spaced-out robot, unaware of himself.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, he still makes choices, he still prefers, he still has agreeable and disagreeable.
[SPEAKER_00]: He has no ownership of any of it, top to bottom.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's why he cannot suffer, because he's not involved with the wrong view.
Would you say that this...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, this is something I read in the Sutta, so I thought it was really nice.
[SPEAKER_01]: That the sense of self is actually a corruption of the mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a corruption.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the mind, without the self, is just a sense of self.
[SPEAKER_01]: The Buddha says it's malleable, wielding and radiant.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sure, but see, if somebody is not free from the sense of self, their thought of a mind that's malleable, radiant, is taken as their self.
[SPEAKER_00]: In other words, that's not what that mind is.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then, now, you are perceiving the idea of not-self, mind free from self, with your current self.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's one of the views that's read out.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you cannot even, theoretically,
[SPEAKER_00]: Understand mind free from the sense of self, free from the ownership, unless you have developed non-ownership here and now.
[SPEAKER_01]: I received another question, very much related to this.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the question goes, if nothing is yours, what is then your mind?
[SPEAKER_01]: If nothing is left, how do you train your mind or what do you train your mind with?
[SPEAKER_00]: What do you mean nothing is left?
[SPEAKER_00]: Everything is left.
[SPEAKER_00]: You haven't touched anything.
[SPEAKER_00]: You just removed your gratuitous emotional ownership of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't need to destroy things to not own them.
[SPEAKER_00]: You just need to stop regarding them as yours, mentally.
[SPEAKER_03]: No.
[SPEAKER_03]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because if they're not yours, they're not your problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now, imagine you have that attitude towards your own senses, towards your own feeling, towards your own intentions, towards your own mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: Imperturbable attitude.
[SPEAKER_00]: In other words, you cannot forget that it cannot be yours, even if you want it to be yours.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's impossible.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_00]: Ownership becomes inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you thoroughly understood the danger, the peril, the escape, and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: The impermanence, the un-ownability of these things.
[SPEAKER_00]: You fully understood and you can... you don't even need to keep telling to yourself, oh, this is not mine.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, nothing can disturb you, then, at all.
[SPEAKER_00]: Absolutely inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_00]: Suffering or any perturbance cannot be even perceived anymore.
I don't try saying...
I'm sorry...
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't try... said somewhere...
[SPEAKER_01]: Every time... so you have these problems, the phone keeps ringing, and every time the phone rings, you pick it up and say, hi, this is Mr. Smith, and... and he said, well, just stop picking up the phone and stop thinking you're Mr. Smith.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, well, you can't help, you can't stop thinking who you are.
[SPEAKER_01]: Can't stop picking up the phone.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, it's not a matter of choice, but you can certainly stop owning how Mr. Smith feels and not acting out of the feeling when you pick up the phone.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, even that Mr. Smith will fade away.
[SPEAKER_02]: Could you, in a certain sense, say, because this act of ownership is interesting, could you say, then, that maybe one way of putting this would be to say, to realize that the structure of the self, so, or the sense of self, is something that is embedded on a
[SPEAKER_02]: In a larger picture, in a larger process, which is basically selfless.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, there's already this sense of...
[SPEAKER_02]: So, the act of ownership, the process of ownership, right?
[SPEAKER_02]: Because there's a slight potential danger here.
[SPEAKER_02]: You might say that, well, you know, where is this sense or process of ownership nested?
[SPEAKER_02]: So, who is it that wants to own?
That's a problem.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, in a certain sense, you kind of have to realize that this is a bottomless process, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_02]: It is a process that does not have yet another self underneath it that would like to grasp.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: In that sense, it's beginningless.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like a vicious circle.
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, like, you have a headache because of the food you eat, and you keep eating the food because
[SPEAKER_00]: So, headache is not a problem, it's a symptom, but at the same time, becomes a problem, because you keep acting out of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Stop acting out of it, it's going to be seen as a symptom, and eventually you're going to discover what the real problem is.
[SPEAKER_00]: You kept thinking that's the problem, and you kept acting out of it, and you kept doing things, they were feeding it in return.
[SPEAKER_01]: Ironically enough.
[SPEAKER_02]: In the Buddhist perspective, so the overall general framework, the question as to how and why this came to be is a known question, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a question of, like when Buddha said, imagine a man being shot by an arrow.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: But instead of allowing that arrow to be pulled out and wound healed, he won't allow it until he finds out who shot him.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why they did so?
[SPEAKER_00]: What did he do to deserve that?
[SPEAKER_00]: Is there anything that he could have avoided?
[SPEAKER_00]: What clan was the man that he... all of these irrelevant things while he's dying.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you need to realize where the priority is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Getting the arrow out.
[SPEAKER_00]: Doesn't matter who, why or what shot me.
[SPEAKER_00]: What matters is I'm shot and I'm bleeding out.
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay, I would have a question.
[SPEAKER_02]: Or did you want to say something?
[SPEAKER_01]: No, I was just trying to fill the silence with some random ramblings, so thank you.
[SPEAKER_02]: We just said that we're not supposed to do that.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, so I'm just...
[SPEAKER_02]: I've been really interested in this notion of
[SPEAKER_02]: ayoniso, manasikāra.
[SPEAKER_02]: First of all, I find it fascinating how basically, for example, in the West, you know, just one particular notion, sati, became the main focus of interest and it's all about mindfulness and everything with mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_03]: Can I just, sorry, can you also explain the word?
[SPEAKER_03]: Because I don't know some of these foreign words and then I just lose the track of the... Yeah, yeah, don't worry.
[SPEAKER_02]: That was the general idea.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, I didn't want to just jump in.
[SPEAKER_02]: This is just a preface or background.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, what I meant is to say, even if at this point nobody knew what this term meant, is that there are a lot of very interesting
[SPEAKER_02]: There are so many fascinating terms and notions in the Pali Canon, and I found it just fascinating how one of them was taken out, and it's now just all the rage.
[SPEAKER_02]: But, with regards to yoniso manasikāra...
[SPEAKER_02]: So, if I understood correctly, yoniso refers etymologically to the word for womb.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: And, it is usually translated as wisely or properly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: And, manasikāra is basically, a literal translation would be mental act, or mentation, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_02]: Mentations.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: But, it is often translated, for some reason, as attention.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, eh...
[SPEAKER_02]: I listened to a talk you gave on this, and I wanted to re-listen it this week.
[SPEAKER_02]: Unfortunately, I was unable to.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, I would just want to, first of all, hear your... how would you translate it?
[SPEAKER_02]: Because, if I remember correctly, you translated it as wise reflection, which I think is closer to what I was reading specifically.
[SPEAKER_00]: Did I?
[SPEAKER_00]: I might have mentioned it, but I don't think I would translate it as wise reflection.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay, no.
[SPEAKER_00]: It would be attention, or rather, attending from the origin.
[SPEAKER_00]: Let's say like that.
[SPEAKER_02]: Attending from the origin.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, again, it's a subtle thing, whichever way you translate it, you're going to have to be explaining it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not going to become self-evident on account of your choice of the terms you use for it, because it's too subtle to be understood.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's one of the prerequisites for the right view.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's a hard thing to clarify for every mind individually.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's exactly that.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you stop and think about it, you always, you know, people always approach things by attending to them.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's, okay, so I look at this, I think of this, I perceive this.
[SPEAKER_00]: womb of that act is what yoniso manasit.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the origin.
[SPEAKER_00]: But see, if you attend to the womb now, of the origin, that becomes the thing you're attending to, which means the womb of that attention is, again, behind you.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's learning to see that behind, without attending it.
[SPEAKER_00]: How can you do that?
[SPEAKER_00]: By knowing it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why context, background, peripheral awareness, all these things I'm talking about, it's all that.
[SPEAKER_00]: It just points at the same thing and that's where the knowledge is.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's why it's so important to realize that all the rage and mainstream practice, it's completely misdirected.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's completely based on perceiving and seeking and seeing and particularizing more and more and more
[SPEAKER_00]: All that's irrelevant.
[SPEAKER_00]: All of that is finding more details at the expense of the context that you don't even know to begin with.
[SPEAKER_00]: And if you do, you wouldn't need any of the...
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't need to know what shape the arrow was, and how it flew, and the physics behind it.
[SPEAKER_00]: All I need to know is that it hurts here and now, and I'm resisting the pain.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the detail level that you need to have.
[SPEAKER_03]: You don't need to know anything else.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's the tendency to not just attend, but to over-attend and attend even more what you attended to.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then, when you tell them, no, it's the origin of the attention, ah, so they attend to that.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like, yeah, but now there is something else as the origin of that attention.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, how can you know it without attending it?
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's the whole practice of learning how to see it peripherally.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because that's what the experience is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Peripheral and actual.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whether you attend to it or not, that is the basis for your attention.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, whatever you're attending now, on account of your senses, is possible, only because your senses, in the form of this body, are still there, simultaneously with what you're attending to, yet you're completely unaware of them.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, learning to be aware, without needing to attend to the senses, because that's impossible.
[SPEAKER_00]: Learning to know that there is an I,
[SPEAKER_00]: But if your measure of mindfulness is what you attend closely, you'll never develop this mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_00]: How can your eye attend itself?
[SPEAKER_00]: But looking in the mirror?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, no.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're attending to the reflection of the eye, for which presence of the eye is necessary, you remain equally unaware of the context.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's yoniso manasikāra.
[SPEAKER_00]: Discerning that which cannot be attended, yet it is there as a necessary basis, is what that wise attention is.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the problem with wise or proper attention, it's not that it's etymologically wrong to translate like that, but the problem is people will think, all right, so I am engaging with the practice of yoniso manasikāra when I stop and think about things.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or certainly not necessarily.
[SPEAKER_00]: So if I just think about things a bit more, that's what the Buddha meant by yoniso manasikāra, which is a prerequisite for sotāpatti.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, it's a bit more than that.
[SPEAKER_02]: It is precisely for this reason, because of what you've just described, that I found this idea of reflection or the term reflection so useful, you know.
[SPEAKER_02]: Precisely this notion where you have... you're not engrossed in the object that is given to you.
[SPEAKER_02]: But you're basically trying to capture the whole setting of it, so the dynamics of your intending towards the object.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you're trying to capture the whole setting, like the alertness, the German word that Heidegger used, without making it an object.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the key.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because even Heidegger made it an object.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because that's the tendency of the mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: You see the context, some people more, some people less, but then you take that for granted and that becomes your object.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you lose context in regard to that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, yes, you want to capture the setting without attending it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's all about... it's not about finding the first context, or the first original object, or something.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's about fully purifying and clarifying and removing any slightest traces of ignorance of the relationship between what you're attending, at any given time, and the necessary basis for that attention.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You understand, with this, this is, all the avijjā is undone.
[SPEAKER_00]: Bhakti-śamupāda fulfilled, completed.
[SPEAKER_00]: With the presence of this, this is.
[SPEAKER_00]: With the presence of the body as the base for the senses, there is sight.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is what I'm looking at, because the body is there.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, knowing that relationship, fully understanding it, that's what needs to be done.
[SPEAKER_02]: If we go now back to what we were talking before about the breathing meditation, could we say that in a certain sense, for example, when you have mindfulness of breath and the body in general, what you're basically doing is precisely
[SPEAKER_02]: You're going to the very, let's say, in a certain sense, foundation, the very basis on which you can basically build this.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because it's, in a certain sense, you're kind of going as as deep as you can go with the dynamic, with this dynamics that you were mentioning.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because breath, as a living, as long as you're alive, breath will be there, the body posture will be there.
[SPEAKER_02]: So there is always like, you know, embodied
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: For as long as it stays the background.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the point.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it's too easy, see, to start attending to the breath and the body as an object of your attention, which means it's not a reference on a background level anymore.
[SPEAKER_00]: But yes, if you know it as being there while experiencing this, or knowing it as being there while experiencing that, you are practicing seeing it as a reference and studying your mind in that knowledge.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, yes, you don't need more than that.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what Buddha said.
[SPEAKER_00]: All these different, you know, satipaṭṭhāna of this, mindfulness of that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or, he's mindful of the body to the extent necessary for the final knowledge.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, to the extent necessary, you have fully understood this context.
[SPEAKER_00]: Extent necessary for uprooting of passion, aversion and the need for distraction and ownership.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's it.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, the question would be...
[SPEAKER_02]: Yes, so I find this very helpful.
[SPEAKER_02]: But the question would be, would it be right to say that, as an intermediary step, so to speak, you make something that is implicit explicit, so that you actually know it.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, what I mean by that is, everybody, in a certain sense, know that he or she breathes, right?
[SPEAKER_02]: You have to make it in the sense that you become aware and that you
[SPEAKER_02]: Understand?
[SPEAKER_02]: And then, you move it into the periphery, but the quality has changed.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: If that's what you were told you're supposed to do, but people are told the opposite.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're supposed to attend it even closer, and even closer, and catch even more specific sensations.
[SPEAKER_00]: If they were not told to do that, there would be no problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, initially, whatever you do, you have to do it by attending it first.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if the knowledge of the peripheral is there, you won't be confused in regard to that.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why Arahant still has attention.
[SPEAKER_00]: He still attends and chooses and, as I said, prefers and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: But there is no more perverting of the order and confusing and putting the second first and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's impossible.
[SPEAKER_02]: This is great.
[SPEAKER_02]: I mean, this has been of tremendous help.
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, gaining the right view is what this group and everyone should be striving for.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Gaining right view.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then we'll be able to understand everything else.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, then you will know what you need to do to be fully enlightened.
[SPEAKER_01]: You also hear accounts of some other teachers, such as, I don't know, Advaita teachers, claiming that they have gained the right view.
[SPEAKER_01]: And what some of them are saying seems correct, seems right.
[SPEAKER_01]: Um, do you think... so, um, according to the suttas, once you get the right view, it's a matter of lifetimes, a few lifetimes before you actually gain enlightenment.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you gain the right view in your previous life, um, probably that's what's going to happen then.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're going to... it's going to be easier for you, probably, in this life too.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, I wouldn't use the word easier.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're just probably going to have less polluted relationship with your own suffering, so you're going to arrive at certain conclusions quicker.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you're going to suffer equally, because you're still born.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: I didn't mean in terms of suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just it seems that some some of these some of these individuals seem to be saying saying it correctly or yes, but but they're not even in the Buddhist tradition.
[SPEAKER_00]: Probably, just the first step, the right view, is probably not so much... Well, yeah, I don't really know what they're saying, so I can't say, you know, they're all wrong, or yes, they're right.
[SPEAKER_00]: But on the individual basis, on the basis of what's being said, I can tell you whether that's along the right lines or not.
[SPEAKER_00]: Many teachers say, oh, just be here now, in the present moment, that's all you have.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then you read the suttas.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, look, the suttas say the same.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, on that superficial level, it sounds the same.
[SPEAKER_00]: But what else do those teachers say?
[SPEAKER_00]: And what else do the suttas say?
[SPEAKER_00]: How do you go about it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Tell me more.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, oh, doctor says he can cure me.
[SPEAKER_00]: This doctor also says he can cure me.
[SPEAKER_00]: Great.
[SPEAKER_00]: I have options.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you don't stay there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now, you go start talking to the doctor and see what you need to do.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if the doctor starts saying some genetic nonsense and doesn't even really just gives you some... and then, well, you're already not trusting that, because surely, if you understood how to approve the illness, you would know how to do it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's often you'll find that.
[SPEAKER_00]: You have all these various eclectic teachers that collect
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, all sorts of, like, Buddhism and other religions, and it does all sound same on that level.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, when somebody's at the bottom, they can't see the difference between, you know, halfway up the mountain and top of the mountain, because it's all just one direction up there.
[SPEAKER_00]: It all looks high, anyway.
[SPEAKER_00]: But there is a difference once you start walking it, like, how far you can go with it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you don't want to ignore that, just because now it feels right, or you don't want to dismiss it either.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just now, because it doesn't necessarily feel right.
[SPEAKER_00]: You want to know what's behind.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay, what's more to this instruction?
[SPEAKER_00]: And same, if the instruction sounds wrong, you want to know why it is wrong.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not just, oh, that's wrong because Ajahn Mahārāj said so.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, do you know for yourself that that's wrong for such and such reason?
[SPEAKER_00]: Why is that inadequate?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, there doesn't seem to be much instruction behind these claims.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the problem then.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thus, claims cannot be taken... like, you should not take them for... that's the whole point.
[SPEAKER_00]: You are making a claim towards the cure, and they're not saying how to cure yourself.
[SPEAKER_00]: Means, you don't know what you're talking about.
[SPEAKER_00]: Means you're a doctor who just pretends to be a doctor.
[SPEAKER_00]: Doctor who just mystifies the solution, but has no actual solution for it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you read the suttas and it's completely the opposite.
[SPEAKER_00]: It tells you exactly what you need to do.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, by the way, it's said not just for other religions.
[SPEAKER_00]: Any... you hear monks speaking, giving instructions, talking about the cure, find out how to go about it from them.
[SPEAKER_00]: If they can't tell you, means they don't know it.
[SPEAKER_00]: As simple as that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if a person knows the cure, he is absolutely... it's inconceivable to not share it with you when he's talking
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, the only thing he's talking about is the cure.
[SPEAKER_00]: But I will not tell you how to do it.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's absolutely no reason for that.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's unthinkable.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, basically, he's trying to convince you that you're not actually sick.
[SPEAKER_00]: Although, we started this conversation on account of mutual illness, now my solution is to teach you how to delude yourself into believing you don't even have a headache.
[SPEAKER_00]: What is a headache anyway?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's always the pinnacle of most of the stuff I heard.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's, well, there is no problem anyway.
[SPEAKER_00]: Stop making a problem, there is no problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: If that were the solution, you would have needed one sutta that says that, and end of story.
[SPEAKER_00]: But see, many people would still think, oh yeah, that's also what the Buddha teaches, yet it's completely earth and sky, opposite things.
[SPEAKER_00]: So the packaging sounds the same, inside, completely different thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you're judging things only on account of the packaging, you're never going to find this out.
[SPEAKER_03]: I have a follow-up question to the earlier one I had.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, if I... boredom is one of the things that is challenging for me.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's...
[SPEAKER_03]: I'm a very active person and I feel that there is something I could learn from it.
[SPEAKER_03]: And it's quite easy to decide...
[SPEAKER_03]: Okay, not easy, but at least doable.
[SPEAKER_03]: To decide, I will not talk, I will not walk, I will not actively do things, I will not watch TV, I will not go for a walk, I'll just sit here.
[SPEAKER_03]: This is not trivial, but easy.
[SPEAKER_03]: But how do you deal with your mind?
[SPEAKER_03]: Because I find it very easy to distract myself with my mind alone.
[SPEAKER_03]: You know, you can start thinking about memories, you can start making plans.
[SPEAKER_03]: Plans are one of the big...
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, practically, maybe you don't have to do it on such a rigid level to begin with.
[SPEAKER_00]: I will not walk, I will not move.
[SPEAKER_00]: But instead, choose on the level that you can sustain for a longer period of time.
[SPEAKER_00]: Such as, I won't switch the TV on, look at my phone, leave the apartment, but I'll move around, drink tea, sit about.
[SPEAKER_00]: I won't sleep, I won't read, I won't distract myself.
[SPEAKER_00]: But I'll stay here.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then the mind will obviously start thinking about various things, initially, but spend three or four hours, maybe longer, like that, the mind will stop, and then you will be back to where you are.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, in other words, you start rigidly, and then you immediately also want to fix the mind to not think about things within that limited framework, because you can't sustain not moving and sitting and not going out and not doing anything for too long.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, find something you can sustain, so that mind can calm down within that, and that's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, you'll see it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Okay, to go more gradually about it and not pull in.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah, exactly, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, there's no problem if you're moving about
[SPEAKER_00]: The problem is when you're doing things on account of restlessness, on account of being bored, and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, again, walking around back and forth in your apartment can provide you only so much entertainment initially.
[SPEAKER_00]: After, very quickly, you'll be bored with it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, keep doing it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why these repetitive actions, like walking meditation, is good.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, oh, I don't want to walk because I'm restless.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, no, walk.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't be too distracted by walking up and down the same lane.
[SPEAKER_03]: I can go for...
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, if that's what you're actively doing, then you can't say you're not doing anything.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're actively making plans.
[SPEAKER_00]: So then, don't do that.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if the mind still keeps popping up with things, that's fine.
[SPEAKER_00]: That will calm down.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you also have to stop fueling it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, yeah, I'll think about this.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'll think about this.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you do have that choice.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you just, like, drop the ball.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you know, when your mind throws you an idea, you don't hold on to it and you say, okay, I'm not pursuing this.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, when the mind throws you the idea, you don't delight in it, you don't welcome it, but you don't deny it either.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, see, the people don't want to stay in that kind of state of in-between.
[SPEAKER_00]: Mind pops up with stuff and I'm enduring, not giving in.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, they want to prevent the mind from popping up with stuff.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's usually meditation techniques come for that purpose.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I can stop thinking because thinking is the problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's you being moved by the thinking.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why there is a problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not the thoughts.
[SPEAKER_00]: But for as long as you think the thoughts are the problem, you're mistaking the symptom for the root, for the root cause.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, don't try to prevent your mind from coming up with this stuff, but certainly prevent yourself from accepting it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's the work, that's the endurance.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you don't need to endure self-inflicted torture and hunger and sleeping on the nails and whatever else to develop your mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: You just need to endure these very things that you have on your day-to-day basis.
[SPEAKER_00]: Mind throwing stuff at you and you're just blindly catching it and accepting it and following it along.
[SPEAKER_00]: Don't do that and you will be training properly.
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay, thank you.
[SPEAKER_02]: I would just have a
[SPEAKER_02]: Short question on the daily practice.
[SPEAKER_02]: And it's just the feeling I got from some of the things that you said.
[SPEAKER_02]: Would it be correct to say that you were not particularly keen on, say, suggesting to anyone who started being involved with Buddhism to have like this daily meditation routine?
[SPEAKER_02]: I got the impression that you would
[SPEAKER_02]: You can have a meditation routine.
[SPEAKER_00]: I would just not agree to the type of meditation people are doing.
[SPEAKER_00]: I wouldn't agree to what they call meditation to be.
[SPEAKER_00]: But yeah, you can... like, routines are useful, certainly in the beginning, but it's like what you perceive to be your duty.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's where the problem is.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's exactly the thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: See, people, I must meditate, you know, because of this, because of that.
[SPEAKER_00]: All of that is rooted in them still not knowing why they're doing it in the first place.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that should be a meditation.
[SPEAKER_00]: Knowing the intentions behind your actions.
[SPEAKER_00]: Developing the context.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, the reason why I sometimes bring up this question about reflection and dispersivity and whatnot is because, for me personally,
[SPEAKER_02]: It was extremely liberating, where I, at a certain point, allowed myself to actually bring more reflective and discursive activity into my meditation, because it somehow seemed that this is like forbidden.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sure, sure.
[SPEAKER_02]: But when at a certain point, for instance, I can give a concrete example, when a very unpleasant feeling arose during meditation,
[SPEAKER_02]: Instead of my trying to either focus on it or focus on the breath, I started asking questions such as, what would it mean for you if this feeling persisted for the rest of your life?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, that's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that was the actual meditation part.
[SPEAKER_00]: See, you broaden the context with a simple question aimed rightly.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, by the way, the suttas are full of that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, Maha Moggallāna, before he developed jhāna, the meditation of meditation, how he developed it?
[SPEAKER_00]: By observing the soles of his feet, or nostrils, or... No.
[SPEAKER_00]: He developed it by sitting down and saying, first jhāna, first jhāna, what is the first jhāna?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, the Buddha said, it's this, this, this, and this.
[SPEAKER_00]: How about I think about all those things and fully understand them?
[SPEAKER_00]: And by doing so, he entered and abided in first jhāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thinking and pondering.
[SPEAKER_00]: Basis for arahantship as well.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yet, today, perception is focus, concentrate, ignore, cover up, shut down.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yes, precisely.
[SPEAKER_02]: And I think that this is... it's really important to kind of dispel this notion, this idea.
[SPEAKER_02]: Again, for me, it was...
[SPEAKER_02]: Every now and again, you would have, in different fields or spheres of your life, these qualitative shifts.
[SPEAKER_00]: For me, it was something this simple, that was like an enormous... No, I know, because, you know, like, I started also as a layman.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, really, just any form of Buddhism.
[SPEAKER_00]: I didn't know right from wrong, in that sense.
[SPEAKER_00]: But in hindsight, I could tell then, what things were along the right lines, and which one weren't.
[SPEAKER_00]: And I was very dutiful when it came to the meditation routine, out in the morning, out in the evening.
[SPEAKER_00]: It didn't matter every day if I had to work or whatever else.
[SPEAKER_00]: And I thought that was my duty.
[SPEAKER_00]: But in hindsight, I realized I would have been better off if I didn't do that and did other things that I didn't know were my duty, but fortunately did them.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, for example, like I would
[SPEAKER_00]: Fulfill my duty of meditating for an hour in the morning, in the evening, and then go out with friends.
[SPEAKER_00]: I would still keep the precepts, that was not the issue, but it would be a fun time.
[SPEAKER_00]: Men, women, company, all of that.
[SPEAKER_00]: And I felt fully justified in doing so because I fulfilled my duty of meditation and, hey, I'm still keeping the precepts.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, in hindsight, I realized I would have been better off if I didn't spend two hours watching the nostrils and if I didn't go out with the friends.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And all those times when I didn't go out like that for the sake of entertainment or distraction, that's why I could then see later on in life.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's where I benefited from.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not that I knew it, but I kept doing it because it felt right.
[SPEAKER_00]: It felt like giving to the weakness otherwise.
[SPEAKER_00]: But nobody told me that that was right thing to do.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's kind of okay, you assume, but no, the right thing is to watch your nostrils and observe your movements and touching, touching, feeling, feeling, sitting, sitting and everything else.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you take that as a duty and it's completely misguided, utterly.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if somebody told me, no, don't do any of that.
[SPEAKER_00]: But every single day of your life,
[SPEAKER_00]: Be aware for the motivation behind your actions and don't act towards lust, aversion and distraction.
[SPEAKER_00]: Doesn't matter what it is.
[SPEAKER_00]: It would have saved me so much time as well.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, if you want to sit quietly and think about wholesome things, that's fine.
[SPEAKER_00]: And make a routine out of it, that's fine.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that's where the benefit is and that's where the work is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, but I fulfill my duty.
[SPEAKER_00]: I can go out, you know, I can, I can, I can enjoy this, I can enjoy it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can, but that's why you're not progressing in the practice.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you realize, okay, so that's where the emphasis should be.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not on this misguided duty of observance of sensations of your body or something, that you won't find in the suttas.
[SPEAKER_00]: Either way.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yes, this resonates very well with me because it was... it's almost as if... there's this idea almost as if meditation was some sort of a syrup that you take.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Then, it kind of does its own thing.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's like a mechanism.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: You set it in motion and I don't know what's going on.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then you just get these results.
[SPEAKER_02]: It just does the thing.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yes.
Yes, okay.
Thank you very much.
A lot of things to be said here, but maybe we save some for next time.